<body>PAGE 60<pb n="60"/><div xml:id="EBA19081105" type="Entry"><p><title>Thursday. Nov. 5th 1908. SS. Princess Irene. </title></p>    <p>We are nearing the end of this part of our voyage – having sailed    from <placeName ref="#New_York">New York</placeName> Saturday the 24th Oct.  <persName  ref="#Newberry_Mary">Mary Newberry</persName> who had been    spending the week there, and <persName ref="#Ohio_Anita">Anita Ohio</persName> went down to see us off.     <persName ref="#Jennings_Walter_Mr_Mrs">Mrs. And Mr. Walter Jennings</persName> and family – 2 children, 2 maids, tutor    and governess, with <persName ref="#Gallandet_Miss">Miss Gallandet</persName>, and sister <persName ref="#Jennings_Miss">Miss Jennings</persName>, were    fellow passengers. They are relatives of <persName ref="#Amkincloss_Hugh">Mrs. Hugh Amkincloss</persName>, who    was <persName ref="#Jennings_Miss">Miss Jennings</persName>.  <persName ref="#Pell_Herbert_Mr_Mrs">Mr. and Mrs. Herbert Pell</persName>, also on board.  A    dull voyage, much rain and warm – I occupied for the 3rd time the    Captain’s charming rooms on the bridge – and what lovely hours of    rest and quiet I had, after all the din and stir of the summer.  The    steamer is comfortable but slow, we reached <placeName ref= "#Gibraltar">Gibraltar</placeName> on the 11th    day and ought to be in <placeName ref="#Naples">Naples</placeName> tonight, only we won’t, at least we    hope to make our steamer tomorrow. </p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081109" type="Entry"><p><title>Monday. Nov. 9. Cairo – Shepheards </title></p><p>We did just make our steamer the‘Preussen’ on Friday – <persName ref="#Pell_Mr_Mrs">Mr. and Mrs. Pell</persName> with us.  We all occupied theCaptain’s and officer’s rooms on the bridge – and were very comfortable– landed at <placeName ref="#Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName> at 3 this P.M. got the train, and at 7 o’clockwere installed in our familiar rooms on the pleasant garden.  We havenever been so early before. Not many people yet. </p>PAGE 61<pb n="61"/>Eldon and <persName ref="#Gorst_Lady">Lady Gorst<persName>. <persName ref="#Pell_Mr_Mrs">Mr. and Mrs. Pell</persName> have been dining with us. Wehave had a busy 10 days in <placeName ref="#Cairo">Cairo</placeName>.  Every one has been so kind.  We wentto <persName ref="#Gorst_Lady">Lady Gorsts</persName> to a garden party – to the <persName ref="#Iddings_Mr_Mrs">Iddings</persName> to dine – and to atea, where we met delightful people.  <persName ref="#Iddings_Mr_Mrs">Mr. and Mrs. Iddings</persName> dined with usthat evening, and <persName ref="#Trefusis_Capt">Capt. Trefusis</persName> – <persName ref="#Maspero">M. Maspero</persName> another evening, and theCapt. Who also lunched with us.  The great event was <persName ref="Davis_Theodore">Theo’s</persName> presentationto the Khedive, which <persName ref="#Iddings_Mr">Mr Iddings</persName> has been trying to persuade him to dofor 3 years – but this year he consented – and he was received in aprivate audience.  <persName ref="#Iddings_Mr">Mr. Iddings</persName> came for him in his own carriage, withhis decorative Kavass, and 2 gorgeous running Sayces, and <persName ref="Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> had toappear in frock coat and top hat at 10 in the morning.  I couldn’t butlaugh when I saw them drive off in such style, for I knew how he hatedit.  It was very successful however, and <persName ref="#Iddings_Mr">Mr. Iddings</persName> told me he hadnever seen the Khedive so interested in an interview.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081120" type="Entry"><p><title>Friday. Nov. 20. </title></p>     <p>In town with <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> this morning, doing last things. <persName ref="#Trefusis_Capt">Capt. Trefusis</persName>     lunched with us.  Our tug took us to the bridge landing at 1     o’clock and we hoped to get through the draw comfortably.  But the     usual scrimmage occurred – and we came near losing the top of our     big boom.  Then we had to get through the new <placeName ref="Giza">Ghizeh</placeName> bridge – we     landed the Capt. And waited until most of the gyassas had passed     through.  We got as far as the big Sugar station, 5 miles below     <placeName ref="Bedreschein">Bedreschein</placeName> – very cold.</p></div>PAGE 62<pb n="62"/><div xml:id="EBA19081121" type="Entry"><p><title>Saturday. Nov. 21.</title></p>     <p>Very busy settling- made <placeName ref="#Wasta">Wasta</placeName> at 5 P.M. warmer.  The river is     tremendous and the current very strong – it is a mighty flood – but     will do great good to the country.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081122" type="Entry"><p><title>23rd Sunday after Trinity. Nov. 22.</title></p>     <p>Sailed at 6 a.m. and tied up at 7 P.M. making 50 miles – warmer and     a wonderful sunset.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081123" type="Entry"><p><title>Monday. Nov. 23rd.</title></p>     <p>Sailed from 6 a.m. to 6 p.m.  Delayed for 4 hours at <placeName ref="#Fadl_Sheik">Sheik Fadl</placeName> for     coal for the tug – have made 40 miles and are now lying 10 miles     below <placeName ref="Minia">Minia</placeName>.  A most wonderful river – no one knows its channel and     our tug goes scalloping about on it in an extraordinary way.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081124" type="Entry"><p><title>Tuesday. Nov. 24th</title></p>     <p>We made an early start at 5:30 and are now at <placeName ref="#Mellawi">Mellawi</placeName> – having made     41-½ miles – beautiful weather, though the wind is cold.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081125" type="Entry"><p><title>Wednesday. Nov. 25th. 48 miles.</title></p>     <p>An early start – we are about 10 miles below <placeName ref="#Asyut">Asyût</placeName>, weather     charming.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081126" type="Entry"><p><title>Thursday. Nov. 26. 40 miles.</title></p>     <p>Reached <placeName ref="#Asyut">Asyût</placeName> at 8 this morning – we were passingPAGE 63<pb n="63"/>the great Weir before I knew it – the draw open and all the sluices –and such a tremendous body of water running through.  Our tug had hardwork to pull us.  Stopped for mail. <persName ref="#Russel_Mr">Mr. Russell</persName> called.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081127" type="Entry"><p><title>Friday. Nov. 27, 45 miles.</title></p>     <p>In spite of strong N.W. wind.  We are lying 6 miles below <placeName ref="#Girga">Girga</placeName>.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081128" type="Entry"><p><title>Saturday. Nov. 28. 32 miles. </title></p><p>A very early start, before dawn.  Such abeautiful hour followed! The sunrise, and this strange, interestingland, and the quiet hour of reading and reflection, nothing can evertake it from me.  A fine day, with strong N.W. wind, which meeting thestrong current of the river, made quite a sea.  We reached <placeName ref="#Nagh_Hamadi">Nagh Hamadi</persName>at 3 o’clock thinking the bridge opened at 3:30 but found it opened at 3o’clock – so we were forced to stay the night.  It was quiet enough –and the late afternoon and evening most lovely.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081129" type="Entry"><p><title>First Sunday in Advent. Nov. 29.</title></p>     <p>We passed the bridge most easily at 7:30 – before I got up.  The     tug took us up as far as the difficult turn at <placeName ref="#Kasr_es_Sayd">Kasr es Sayd</placeName> – then     left us with much hearty leave-takings and receiving of liberal     backsheesh.  The day was absolutely calm, and we were left alone in     the middle of the river, with both sails limply hanging – we have     tracked, pulled to the anchor and sailed a little very quietly and     are now lyingPAGE 64<pb n="64"/>within sight of  <placeName ref="#Dishneh">Dishneh</placeName> – a most exquisite evening.  17 miles. </p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081130" type="Entry"><p><title>Monday. Nov. 30. 42 ½ miles. </title></p>     <p>Made an early start this morning in a good wind, and reached this     high bank, one mile below <placeName ref="#Naqada">Nagada</placeName> at 5.30.  An exciting day – the     boat careering madly along – sailors shouting – sails changing, and     all the clamor of a sharp sailing.  The morning was delicious – I     was on deck all the time until we were delayed by a gyassa which     cut across our bow in an awkward way, and going immediately upon     the sand just in front of us, we had to pull up so sharply that we     went with a  great thump on the bank – there was a great tumbling     about of all movable things – and when I came below to see about it     - I found <persName ref="Amelie">Amelie</persName>, <persName ref="#Jones_Daniel">Jones</persName>, <persName ref="#Hassein">Hassein</persName>, and <persName ref="#Hassoun">Hassoun</persName> busy setting     everything straight.  Last year we came on the boat Nov. 30.  We     are much in advance this year! </p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081201" type="Entry"><p><title>Tuesday. Dec. 1st. 23-½ miles.</title></p>     <p><placeName ref="#Luxor">Luxor</placeName>. A high wind, but not favourable, all day.  However we came     gallantly in with sails filled at 5.30 and found ourselves the     first arrival of the season. Everyone was on the lookout for us,     and we were told that we made a splendid appearance, as we rushed     along past the town to our old mooring ground on the island.      <persName ref="#Jones_Harold">Harold Jones</persName> was waiting for us at the Winter Palace, Tuesday being     his off day.  He came over at once, and stayed to dinner and gave     us the news.  It took us 10 days and part of another day from <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>     here. </p></div>PAGE 65<pb n="65"/><div xml:id="EBA19081201" type="Entry"><p><title>Wednesday. Dec. 2nd.</title></p>     <p>I have had a quietly busy and most pleasant day at home.  Theo and     <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> were at <placeName ref="#Karnak">Karnak</placeName> and the <placeName ref="Luxor">Luxor</placeName> temple.  A big mail last     night, and reams of papers. No bad news.  <persName ref="Mathilde">Mathilde</persName> better.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081203" type="Entry"><p><title>Thursday. Dec. 3rd.</title></p>     <p><persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> and <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> went to the Valley today and did not get back     until 4 o’clock.  They report the road very bad as far as the     bridge. <persName ref="#Jones_Harold">Harold</persName> is working between <persName ref="#Horemheb">Hor-em-heb</persName> and <persName ref="#Amenhotep_II">Amenhotep II</persName> tomb.      Cold. </p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081204" type="Entry"><p><title>Friday. Dec. 4th.</p></title>     <p><persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> and <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> at <placeName ref="#Karnak">Karnak</placeName> today – and I over to the town.  <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Mr. and     Mrs. Weigall</persName> were here this afternoon.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081205" type="Entry"><p><title>Saturday. Dec. 5th.</title></p>     <p><persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> at the boat very busy with letters.  <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> and I went over     and called on <persName ref="#Buchanan_Carrie">Miss Buchanan</persName> – such a very nice visit.  The school     very prospering – over 280 pupils.  The place has much improved – a     fine stone wall all about it – and a beautiful garden making.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081206" type="Entry"><p><title>Second Sunday in Advent. Dec. 6.</title></p>     <p>A quiet day at home – <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> and <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> over at the Valley. The     roads and embankments have been so spoiled by the river, that they     are well nigh impossible – and I cannot get over in my chair until     theyPAGE 66<pb n="66"/>are better. Last night about 12 o’clock, I was aroused by cries that Ithought must be those of a jackal – it proved to have been a man in theriver.  Six men had gone to our opposite neighbor <persName ref="#Insinger_Mr">Mr. Insingers</persName>, to roband steal.  They overpowered the night watchman, and one of them gotinto the house.  <persName ref="#Insinger_Mr">Mr. Insinger</persName> sent a shot at the man, who ran, followedby <persName ref="#Insinger_Mr">Mr. Insinger</persName> firing at him – the man took to the river, and found thecurrent so strong that he screamed for help.  The police appeared andcaught the man, who gave the names of the men with him.  There is agreat deal of lawlessness about the country and some alarm felt.</p></div><div xml:id="EBA19081207" type="Entry">Monday. Dec. 7th.     <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> and I went to see <persName ref="#Buchanan_Carrie">Miss Buchanan</persName> this morning – such a brave     little woman.  Our nights are now most beautiful – full moon.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081208" type="Entry">Tuesday. Dec. 8th.     Beautiful weather – <persName ref="#Jones_Harold">Harold Jones</persName> came over this morning and stayed     all night.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081209" type="Entry">Wednesday. Dec. 9th.     A cold day – <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Mr. and Mrs. Weigall</persName> here this afternoon.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081210" type="Entry">Thursday. Dec. 10th.     <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> and I went over to <placeName ref="#Luxor">Luxor</placeName> and drove out to see Mrs. Weigall.      Found <persName ref="#Whymper_Charles">Mr. Whymper</persName> and <persName ref="#Dunn_Dr">Dr. Dunn</persName> there.  Afterwards to the Savoy</div>PAGE 67<pb n="67"/>to call on <persName ref="#Quibell_Mr">Mrs. Quibell</persName> and <persName ref="#Pirie_Miss">Miss Pirie</persName> – not at home – then asked for<persName ref="#Bruce_Miss">Miss Bruce</persName> and <persName ref="#Dobie_Miss">Miss Dobie</persName> – the former in bed – and I went up to herroom to see her.  <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> in the Valley today.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081211" type="Entry">Friday. Dec. 11.     Another fine day – but still cold.  Everybody growling about the     continued cold.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081212" type="Entry">Saturday. Dec. 12th.     Very busy with catalogues and gardening plans.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081213" type="Entry">Third Sunday in Advent. Dec. 13.     <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> and <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> in the Valley.  Had a nice visit from <persName ref="Carter_Howard">Mr. Carter</persName>     this morning – <persName ref="#Whymper_Charles">Mr. Whymper</persName>, <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Mr. and Mrs. Weigall</persName> dined with us, a     pleasant evening.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081214" type="Entry">Monday. Dec. 14th.     Rather warmer today.  <persName ref="#Quibell_Mr">Mrs. Quibell</persName> and <persName ref="#Pirie_Miss">Miss Pirie</persName>.  So glad     to see them.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081215" type="Entry">Tuesday. Dec. 15th.     <persName ref="#Jones_Harold">Harold Jones</persNamer> lunched here – having spent the night with the     <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Weigalls</persName> – and intending to return there for the night.  <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> and     <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> at <placeName ref="#Dar_el_Bahari">Der el Bahari</placeName>.</div>PAGE 68<pb n="68"/><div xml:id="EBA19081216" type="Entry">Wednesday. Dec. 16th.     In doors, except for a long walk on the sands – <persName ref="#Bruce_Miss">Miss Bruce</persName>      and <persName ref="#Dobie_Miss">Miss Dobie</persName> here this afternoon.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081221" type="Entry">Monday. Dec. 21st.     <persName ref="#Campbell_Dr_Mrs">Dr. and Mrs. Campbell</persName> and daughter came this afternoon, bringing     with them <persName ref="#d'Albertis_Count_Countess">Count and Countess d’Albertis</persName> of Genoa.  <persName ref="#Jones_Harold">Harold Jones</persName>     later, all stayed to tea.  The days are so quiet and monotonous     there is little to chronicle.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081223" type="Entry">Wednesday. Dec. 23rd.     The ‘<name type="boat">Scarab</name>’ and ‘<name type = "boat">Osiris</name>’ up today, and came to our side, directly     behind us.  The <name type="boat">Scarab</name> almost poking her nose into my cabin.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081225" type="Entry">Friday. Dec. 25th.     <persName ref="#Paget_Almerio">Mr. Almerio Paget</persName> called this morning.  He is on the <name type="boat">Scarab</name> with     his wife (Pauline Whitney) and family.  We had our usual little     celebration with the men this morning.  The usual Christmas     festivities. <persName ref="#Jones_Harold">Harold</persName> spent the night here – and with those 3 nice     men <persName ref="#Whymper_Charles">Mr. Whymper</persName>, and <persName ref="#Nicol_Mr">Mr. Nicol</persName>, dined here.  <persName ref="#Smith_Joseph_Lindon">Joe Smith</persName> arrived with     his wife today, they are staying at <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Weigalls</persName>.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081229" type="Entry">Tuesday. Dec. 29th.     At tea with the <persName ref="#Scofield_Mr_Mrs">Scofields</persName> on the <name type="boat">Maat</name>.  <persName ref="#Jones_Harold">Harold</persName> here for the day.      <persName ref="#Lagge_Mr">Mr. F. Lagge</persName> and his friend <persName ref="#Pease_Mr">Mr. Pease</persName> dined with us.  The<persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> hasPAGE 69<pb n="69"/>bought one of <persName ref="#Nicol_Mr">Mr. Nicol’s</persName> best pictures.  The <name type="boat">Scarab<name> with the <persName ref="#Paget_Mr_Mrs">Pagets</persName> andthe <name type="boat">Osiris</name> with <persName ref="#Paget_Arthur">Sir Arthur and Lady Paget</persName> went up today. Lovely weather.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081230" type="Entry">Wednesday. Dec. 30th.     <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Mrs. Weigall</persName>, <persName ref="#Smith_Joseph_Lindon">Mrs. Smith</persName>, and <persName ref="#Buchanan_Carrie">Miss Buchanan</persName> lunched here.  <persName ref="#Baron_de_Vos">Baron de     Vos</persName> of the Dongela called, also <persName ref="#Mandsley_Mr">Mr. Mandsley</persName> bringing the horrible     news of the <placeName ref="#Messina">Messina</placeName> earthquake.</div><div xml:id="EBA19081231" type="Entry">Thursday. Dec. 31st.     <persName ref="#Scofield_Grace">Miss Grace Scofield</persName>, <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> and I, and <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> went to the Valley     today, lunched in our comfortable little stone house.  Perfect day.<div xml:id="EBA19090112" type="Entry">Jan. 12th. Tuesday.     Various happenings social and otherwise since the month came in.      <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Mrs. Weigall and <persName ref="#Smith_Joseph_Lindon">Corinna Smith</persName> come every Saturday morning to read.     <persName ref="#Walter_Brown">Mr. and Mrs. Walter Brown</persName> of Venice are here for a month, with     Mrs. B’s mother, <persName ref="#Beckwith_Mrs">Mrs. Beckwith<persName>.  <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> had <persName ref="#Nicol_Mr">Mr. Nicol</persName> out one day in     the Valley wishing to show him the western valley.  <persName ref="#Taft_Henry">Mrs. Henry Taft</persName>     with her daughters dined with us one evening, with <persName ref="#Nicol_Mr">Mr. Nicol</persName>,     <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Weigall</persName> and <persName ref="Smith_Joseph_Lindon">Joe Smith</persName>.  Then we had them (Mrs. and Miss Taft) out     to the Valley next day.  The <persName ref="#Jennings_Mr_Mrs">Jennings</persName> have turned up.  <persName ref="#Baron_de_Vos">Baron de Vos</persName>     called – some things quite interesting have been found in the     debris of the pit tomb <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> has been working in lately.  Bits of     gold foil, stamped with the cartouches ofPAGE 70<pb n="70"/><persName ref="#Tutankhamun">Thut-ankh-amon</persName>, <persName ref="#Ay">Ai</persName> and <persName ref="#Ankhesenamun">S-ankh-aten</persName>, wife of T.A.A.  She was the 3rddaughter of <persName ref="#Akhenaten">Akenaten</persName>.</div><div xml:id="EBA19090115" type="Entry">Friday. Jan. 15th.     <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> again in the Valley – <persName ref="#Erskine_David_C">Mr. Erskine</persName> has turned up again – he     lunched with <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName> today.</div><div xml:id="EBA19090116" type="Entry">Saturday. Jan 16th.     <persName ref="#Weigall_Arthur">Hortense Weigall</persName>, and <persName ref="#Smith_Corinna">Corinna Smith</persName> were her this morning for the     usual reading.  They are all camping out up at the Beit Wilkinson     place – and <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> and I went up there to lunch.  <persName ref="#Erskine_David_C">Mr. Erskine</persName> and     <persName ref="#Campbell_Colins">Rev. Colins Campbell</persName> were there – a pleasant day.</div><div xml:id="EBA19090121" type="Entry">Jan. 21 – Thursday.     <persName ref="Jones_Harold">Harold</persName> found yesterday in the last corner of the pit tomb, a most     lovely alabaster statuette of a woman – about 9 in. high, the most     perfect specimen of Egyptian art I have ever seen, and in perfect     condition.  To think of her lying under that hard mud for nearly     3000 years! no inscription.  It is thought it may represent the     wife of <persName ref="#Tutankhamun">Thut-ankh-amen</persName>.  <persName ref="#Davis_Theodore">Theo</persName>, <persName ref="#Knagenbjelm_Eleanor">Eleanor</persName> and <persName ref="#Maspero">M. and Mme. Maspero</persName> in     the valley today.  Lovely weather.</div><div xml:id="EBA19090124" type="Entry">Third Sunday after Epiphany.  Jan. 24th.     We were distressed and amazed this morning at breakfast toPAGE 71<pb n="71"/>Hear of poor <persName ref="#Smith_Corinna">Corinna’s</persName> disaster.  She was here yesterday morning asusual.  I thought she looked very tired and troubled.  She had manythings to do in town, before she went back to their camp.  The <persName ref="#Petrie_Flinders">Petries</persName>were dining with them.  She was then suffering extremely from pain inone eye – which grew so bad that she became delirious.  They (she and<persName ref="#Smith_Joseph_Lindon">Joe</persName>) got some donkeys and came at a walk all the way to the river, wherethey quietly aroused some of our sailors, who rowed them across to Luxorto the doctor.  He advised them to go at once to Cairo – and they noware on their way there.  It is a hideous experience for the poor things– a very bad case of opthalmia.  The <persName ref="#Brown_Walter">Walter Browns</persName> here to tea. </div>81908-19098 8</body>